# Pratiksha Shrestha

+1 (347) 686 1391 / pratiksha.shrestha97@gmail.com / github.com/prati1 | prati1.github.io | linkedin.com/in/pratiksha-shrestha

## **SUMMARY**

Software developer with 5+ years of experience building applications for e-commerce, resource and data management. Proficient in Python, Node.js, JavaScript, React, MySQL, MongoDB, and AWS with expertise spanning front-end, back-end, and RESTful web services, Demonstrated skills in OOP concepts, microservices and serverless architecture, and Solidity development for Web3 DApps in blockchain. Experienced on using version control systems such as Git, bitbucket, GitLab for continuous integration and development.

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages & Runtime Env: Python, JavaScript, TypeScript, Node.js, PHP, C++, Solidity, Shell Script

Frameworks & Packages: Express.js, React.js, Vue.js, Laravel, jQuery, Selenium, Chai, NPM, Gradle, Gulp, Knex.js, Numpy Databases: MySQL, MongoDB, MariaDB, DocumentDB, Oracle Autonomous Database

Software/Technology: Amazon Web Services (AWS Lambda, Batch, RDS, EC2, S3, ECS, Cognito, CloudWatch, CodePipeline, CodeDeploy, SNS, SES), Microservices, Redis, Agile, Database Optimization, Git, Linux, Docker, CI/CD, Ajax, XML

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Full-Stack Developer (Graduate Assistant) | Myaamia Center, Miami University, Ohio

August 2022 – Present

- Designed and built intuitive web admin panel for tribal language revitalization, enhancing engagement and accessibility
- Led database architecture design and development for a dynamic survey management and data analysis platform. Supported 10+ surveys, implementing advanced filtering, sorting, and data mapping across interconnected survey datasets.
- Developed a tool for efficient multipart uploads and streamed downloads for large files on AWS S3, effectively preventing web wait timeout issues.
- Migrated from traditional server to AWS cloud services with zero server downtime and data loss

Tech Stack: Laravel, PHP, jQuery, JavaScript, Python, AWS, MariaDB, Docker, Rest API, Puppet

**Software Developer** | *Proshore, Netherlands (From Proshore Nepal)* 

March 2019 - June 2022

- Led development of B2B web applications in cross-functional team of 7-10 members following Agile SCRUM approach
- Achieved 400% performance boost with targeted database optimization & codebase enhancement (5x faster response time)
- Implemented factory pattern with multi-threading for efficient large database parsing in Python batch jobs
- Optimized SOL queries, re-indexed tables, implemented client-server database model with database partitioning and sharding along with Redis cache for frequently accessed data to reduce server load and improve performance
- Implemented e-commerce data synchronization across 4 third-party vendor systems for improved data accuracy & efficiency
- Migrated legacy monolithic application to microservices model hosted in AWS EC2 using AWS Gateway API
- Engineered **continuous deployment** pipeline reducing deployment time by 70% with improved release and rollback process

Tech Stack: Node.js, Python, JavaScript, MySQL, DocumentDB, AWS, Docker, Kubernetes, Redis, jQuery, Vue.js, Knex.js, Express.js, Mollie API, REST API, Filezilla, FTP, SMTP, cXML, Jira, Postman, Selenium, Chai

## Associate Software Engineer | GrowByData Services Pvt. Ltd

August 2018 - February 2019

- Researched and implemented search engine optimization strategies resulting in increased visibility of e-commerce stores
- Incorporated search engine spidering, crawling, indexing and set up tests and campaigns for A/B testing and report generation
- Developed client-requested features on sites hosted in e-commerce platforms

Tech Stack: JavaScript, Node.js, jQuery, Shopify, BigCommerce, Magento, ABTasty, Screaming Frog, Google Tag Manager

## **EDUCATION**

**Master Of Science in Computer Science** 

Miami University of Oxford, Ohio

**B.E.** Computer Engineering

Kathmandu University, Nepal

August 2022 – May 2024 (Expected)

CGPA: 4.00/4.00 (Ongoing)

**August 2014 – October 2018** 

CGPA: 3.63 /4.00

Women Leaders in Technology (WLiT) | Technical Committee Member/Instructor

**August 2018 – June 2022** 

- Conducted web development sessions in Node.js, JavaScript and jQuery at WLiT bootcamp 2020/21, and 2021/22
- Mentored undergraduate female students, guiding them towards their professional aspirations and nurturing leadership abilities

#### **PROJECTS**

Review Rewards | Solidity, TypeScript, React.js, Node.js, OracleDB, EVM, NFT, Hardhat, zkSNARK, SBT, OpenGSN

- Developed and deployed secure, privacy-focused web3 application for academic peer review on blockchain
- Implemented Soul Bound Tokens (SBT); non-transferable NFTs to recognize reviewers for their contribution
- Wrote unit tests to compute accuracy and gas efficients of Solidity smart contracts

suggestAbook | Python, JavaScript, Node.js, React.js, Flask, Numy, Pandas

- Book recommendation system utilizing Collaborative Filtering approach
  - Applied k-Nearest neighbor approach on user-item sparse matrix to offer tailored book recommendation based on current read